<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reproducible Research on Ed Hagen</title>
    <link>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/categories/reproducible-research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reproducible Research on Ed Hagen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/categories/reproducible-research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The replication crisis: our statistics don&#39;t suck, our theories do</title>
      <link>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/2018/01/16/the-replication-crisis-our-statistics-don-t-suck-our-theories-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/2018/01/16/the-replication-crisis-our-statistics-don-t-suck-our-theories-do/</guid>
      <description>Every genuine test of a theory is an attempt to falsify it, or to refute it. Karl Popper, 1963.
  Arthur: Brother Maynard! Bring up the Holy Hand Grenade!….How does it, um– how does it work?
  Second Brother: And the Lord spake, saying, “First shalt thou take out the Holy Pin. Then, shalt thou count to three. No more. No less. Three shalt be the number thou shalt count, and the number of the counting shall be three.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data dredging is the Dionysian soul of science</title>
      <link>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/2018/01/01/data-dredging-is-the-dionysian-soul-of-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/2018/01/01/data-dredging-is-the-dionysian-soul-of-science/</guid>
      <description>Figure 1: Good and Evil Angels. Plate 4 of The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. From The William Blake Archive.  Yin and Yang. Apollo and Dionysus. Heaven and Hell. Id and Superego. Reason and Emotion. Spock and McCoy. Many intellectual and moral frameworks are structured around two, often opposing, elements. If one element gains the upper hand over the other, beware. William Blake, for example, in The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, took aim at the imbalance he saw in Christian theology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Put your data in an R package</title>
      <link>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/2017/10/18/put-your-data-in-an-r-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://grasshoppermouse.github.io/2017/10/18/put-your-data-in-an-r-package/</guid>
      <description>I used to write long R scripts that imported data files, created new variables, reshaped the data, reshaped it again, and spit out results along the way, all in one file.
That worked so long as I never wanted to use that data again. But what if I did? Should I just tack on more code for the new analysis, and then even more code for yet more analyses? That approach will litter your environment with objects that are irrelevant for, and might even interfere with, a particular analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>